اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
إن الحمد لله، نحمده ونستعينه ونستغفره ونستهديه،
ونعوذ بالله من شرور أنفسنا ومن سيئات أعمالنا،
من يهده الله فلا مضل له ومن يضلل فلا هادي له،
وأشهد أن لا إله إلا الله وأشهد أن محمدرسول الله، امَّا بعد
ونحمدالله عزوجل الذى بنعمت اجتمع الصالحات
We praise Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, whom without Him, no good could happened and all blessings are from Him.
We thank Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and we say; Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله) and then; Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله) and then; Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله);
Who made it possible for us to worship Him.
If it wasn't for Him allowing us and assisting us to do so;
we wouldn't have been able to make one Tasbeeha(تسبيهه) or one Tahlila(تحليله) or one Takbeera(تكبيره) or one Raka'ah(ركعه) or to fast one day.
It is all from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and his Tawfeeq(توفيق) and assistance.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى saved Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) from the strongest man and regime and army and nation, on the face of the earth.
To Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; there is nothing that is the superpower.
There is no one who is strong.
There is no government that is powerful.
For Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; they are all under Him and they are all His servants.
And for Allahسُبحانه وتعالى with Kun Fayakun(كُن فَيَكُون); everything is created or anything can be destroyed.
وَإِذْ أَنجَيْنَاكُم مِّنْ آلِ فِرْعَوْنَ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; We saved you from Firaun(فرعون) and his people.
Blessing from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Banu Israel(بنو اسرائيل) saw the miracle of Allah in front of their own eyes.
They saw the sea split into two portions which seemed like mountains.
And then they saw Firaun(فرعون) and his army drowning.
And they saw how Allahسُبحانه وتعالى delivered them to safety.
What was the first thing they did, when they reached to safety?
Banu Israel(بنو اسرائيل) the first thing they did, when they were with Musa(موسى),
when they were traveling into a new land, finally they are in freedom now, released from the servitude of Firaun(فرعون)?
Banu Israel(بنو اسرائيل) saw some men worshipping some idols.
They went to Musa(موسى) and they said;
ٱجْعَل لَّنَآ إِلَٰهًا كَمَا لَهُمْ ءَالِهَةٌ ۚ
They said; Oh Musa(موسى)! Can you create for us or make for us a god, like they have gods.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَجَٰوَزْنَا بِبَنِىٓ إِسْرَٰٓءِيلَ ٱلْبَحْرَ فَأَتَوْاْ عَلَىٰ قَوْمٍۢ يَعْكُفُونَ عَلَىٰٓ أَصْنَامٍۢ لَّهُمْ ۚ
قَالُواْ يَٰمُوسَى ٱجْعَل لَّنَآ إِلَٰهًا كَمَا لَهُمْ ءَالِهَةٌ ۚ
And we brought the children of Israel(اسرائيل) with safety across the sea,
and they came upon people devoted to some of their idols in worship.
They said; Oh Moses! Make for us a God as they have Gods.
Subhanallahil-Azeem(سُبحَانَ اللهِ العَظِيم)! you just came out from Egypt.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى saved you and you saw the miracles of Allah with your own eyes.
You saw the miracles of Allah, assisting Musa(موسى) and assisting you and you were helpless and you couldn't do anything for yourselves.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى performs these miracles in front of your own eyes.
And then you ask Musa(موسى) to create for you a god, like they have Gods.
Banu Israel(بنو اسرائيل) they knew about Allah and they believed in Allah, Don't understand this wrong.
Don't think that Banu Israel(بنو اسرائيل) wanted to replace the religion with something else.
No!
They believed in Allah and they knew that Allah is the one who helped them and assisted them.
But when they saw what the other people are doing, they wanted to have something similar to them.
They are not satisfied with what they had.
They have an inferiority complex.
So they think that these gods are gonna bring them closer to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى or something.
Ibn Khaldoon(اِبن خَلدُون) says something interesting.
He says that, always weak nations imitate the strong nations.
الضعيف يتشبه بالقوي
The weak imitates the strong.
Banu Israel(بنو اسرائيل) were weak in Egypt, and they came out of Egypt,
now they are in freedom, but they're still thinking with the weak mentality.
So they always think that the others have something better than them.
And you find among the Muslims who are weak today,
those of them who are not proud with what Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given them,
they're always trying to find ways to imitate the others.
And who are they imitating?
They're imitating the West.
Because the West is strong.
So you find that the Muslim wants to look like the non-believers.
He wants to act like the non-believers.
He wants to celebrate like the non-believers.
He wants to do everything; the way the non-believers are acting.
One of the prominent priests of the Catholic Church in Italy.
So this priest wrote a letter to the Pope.
In that letter, he said; If you would just see the state of our Christian men;
he was talking about Alfursaan(اَلفُرسَان); these are the Knights.
The Christian churches to send these Knights to raid the Muslim world,
they would go to the Holy Land and these were very powerful small bands of horsemen.
And then they would dispatch them to the Muslim world to cause corruption.
And by the way, not only were they causing corruption on land, but it also happened in the sea.
Do you know who the pirates?
What are the pirates?
How were the pirates founded?
And do you know, who they were fighting?
Piracy; the whole issue of piracy and pirates in the sea, which we see a lot of cartoons and movies about.
It was started and invented to fight the Muslims in the Mediterranean Sea.
That is how piracy started.
Because the Mediterranean Sea was an Islamic sea for a very long time,
with Al-Abbaseen(اَلعَبَّاسِين) and then Al-Usmaneen(اَلعُثمَانِين) was the power in the Mediterranean Sea.
So these pirates would go and they would raid the Muslim merchant; who are travelling in the Mediterranean Sea, anyway.
So this priest wrote a letter to the Pope.
He said; If you would see how our men try to dress like the Muslims and they learn Arabic
and they write poetry of romance and love in Arabic better, than the Arabs.
Because the Muslims in that time were strong.
So you find that the weak is always trying to imitate the strong.
And now, things reversed.
So you have know, the Muslim is trying to imitate the ones who are strong.
But the Muslim should always believe that the strength is from Allah.
And the honor belongs to Allah.
العِزَّةُ للَّهِ‏ِ ولِرَسولِهِ ولِلمُؤمِنينَ‏
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; All honor belongs to Allah and His messenger and to the believers.
What we are going through now is a temporary state; it is not permanent.
So Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are still thinking with that inferior; weak mentality.
So, they said;
ٱجْعَل لَّنَآ ءَالِهَةٌ ۚ ٱجْعَل لَّنَآ إِلَٰهًا كَمَا لَهُمْ ءَالِهَةٌ ۚ
This action in itself; is it a sin or is it Kuffr(كفر)?
It is Kuffr(كفر).
It is disbelief.
When you're asking for a god, besides Allah that is Kuffr(كفر).
But what did Musa(موسى) tell them?
Did he say you are non believers, you are Kuffar(كفار)?
No, he didn't.
He said;
أَنتُمْ قَوْمٌ تَجْهَلُونَ۝
You are people who are ignorant.
So he excuse them with their ignorance,
but he taught them, and whoever refuses after they received the message, then that is disbelief.
So Musa(موسى) now is teaching them; he said;
قَالَ إِنَّكُمْ قَوْمٌ تَجْهَلُونَ۝
You are people who are ignorant.
And then he told them;
إِنَّ هَؤُلَاءِ مُتَبَّرٌ مَا هُمْ فِيهِ وَبَاطِلٌ مَا كَانُوا يَعْمَلُونَ۝
Verily, these people will be destroyed; for that which they engaged in, and all that they're doing is in vain.
These people don't think that they're strong; don't think that they're powerful; they are going to be destroyed,
what they're doing is; wrong.
قَالَ أَغَيْرَ اللَّهِ أَبْغِيكُمْ إِلَٰهًا وَهُوَ فَضَّلَكُمْ عَلَى الْعَالَمِينَ۝
He said; Shall I seek for you a god other than Allah while, He Has given you superiority over mankind?
Musa(موسى) is telling Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) that, Allah has chosen you.
They were the chosen people of Allah.
They were the nation whom Allah chose.
Even though up to that moment, they were still weak, and they didn't have any Khilafah(خِلَافَه), and they didn't have any nation, and they didn't have any power.
Nevertheless, they were still the best.
And the Muslims need to read the Ayah(آية) of Qur'an, where Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
كُنْتُمْ خَيْرَ أُمَّةٍ أُخْرِجَتْ لِلنَّاسِ
You were the best nation produced for mankind.
You are the best nation that was brought forth for humanity.
So even if we are in a slump in a weak moment,
we should still understand and realize that we have; what can make us the best and the chosen people of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So Musa(موسى) is telling Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) that; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given you superiority over mankind.
He has chosen you.
Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) left Egypt, and they were promised the Holy Land, Jerusalem and the land surrounding it.
So Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are traveled toward that direction.
They arrived next to Jerusalem.
Musa(موسى) told his people; Let's attack!
Here's Jerusalem, we can see it with our own eyes; Let's attack!
In that time, it was ruled by Al-Amaleeq(اَلْعَمَالِيْق); certain disbelieving nation.
They were the rulers of the Holy Land.
And Musa(موسى) told Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); Allah has promised you with this land; so let's attack!
وَإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِقَوْمِهِۦ يَٰقَوْمِ ٱذْكُرُواْ نِعْمَةَ ٱللَّهِ عَلَيْكُمْ إِذْ جَعَلَ فِيكُمْ أَنۢبِيَآءَ وَجَعَلَكُم مُّلُوكًا وَءَاتَىٰكُم
وَءَاتَىٰكُم مَّا لَمْ يُؤْتِ أَحَدًا مِّنَ ٱلْعَٰلَمِينَ۝
يَا قَوْمِ ادْخُلُوا الْأَرْضَ الْمُقَدَّسَةَ الَّتِي كَتَبَ اللَّهُ لَكُمْ وَلَا تَرْتَدُّوا عَلَىٰ أَدْبَارِكُمْ
وَلَا تَرْتَدُّوا عَلَىٰ أَدْبَارِكُمْ فَتَنقَلِبُوا خَاسِرِينَ۝
Oh my people! enter the Holy Land which Allah has assigned to you.
Do not turn back in fighting.
الفرار من الزحف
Turning your back in the battle; is one of the major sins in Islam.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has counted in one Hadith(حديث); seven major sins.
One of them is;
الفرار من الزحف
Turning your back to the battlefield and running away.
It's a major sin and the Ulama(عُلَمَا) say that, doing that, can destroy your deeds;
can destroy them; it just destroy all what you have done.
تحبط الاعمال
And Musa(موسى) is telling his people;
وَلَا تَرْتَدُّوا
Do not turn your back in fighting.
فَتَنقَلِبُوا خَاسِرِينَ۝
Then you will be returned as losers.
If you turn your back away; you will return as losers.
Not only did Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) turn their back to their enemy; they refuse to fight, to start with.
It wasn't the matter of turning your back in the battlefield.
They said; We are not going to fight.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قَالُواْ يَٰمُوسَىٰٓ إِنَّ فِيهَا قَوْمًا جَبَّارِينَ وَإِنَّا لَن نَّدْخُلَهَا حَتَّىٰ يَخْرُجُواْ مِنْهَا
وَإِنَّا لَن نَّدْخُلَهَا حَتَّىٰ يَخْرُجُواْ مِنْهَا فَإِن يَخْرُجُواْ مِنْهَا فَإِنَّا دَٰخِلُونَ۝
They said; Oh Musa(موسى)! In it are a people of great strength.
So what, if there are people of great strength.
They said; And we shall never enter it till they leave it.
When they leave, then we will enter.
Look at this; they said that, the people in there are powerful and strong.
They said; They're powerful and strong.
So we're not gonna get in there until, these people leave.
How do you think people who are powerful and strong are gonna vacate it for you?
You already said that, they're powerful and strong.
Do you accept, expect them to walk out and tell you come on in?
You're already said that, these are people who are strong.
But this is the negative passive stance of people who are humiliated.
They want victory without paying the price.
Let them leave and then we're gonna walk in.
We want the victory; we want the Holy Land
but we don't want to fight;
we don't want to sacrifice;
we don't want to pay any wealth;
we don't want to give our souls;
we don't want to put any effort;
we want to go in there, in an effortless fashion.
فَيَخْرُجُواْ مِنْهَا، إِنَّا دَٰخِلُونَ۝
Let them leave, first and then we're gonna walk in.
But there's still some good among them, so two men came ahead.
قَالَ رَجُلَانِ مِنَ ٱلَّذِينَ يَخَافُونَ أَنْعَمَ ٱللَّهُ عَلَيْهِمَا ٱدْخُلُواْ عَلَيْهِمُ ٱلْبَابَ فَإِذَا دَخَلْتُمُوهُ فَإِنَّكُمْ غَٰلِبُونَ ۚ
Two men of those who feared Allah; on whom Allah had bestowed His grace, said;
Assault them through the gate for when you are in; victory will be yours.
They said; You attack them; open up the gate and that will be enough to defeat the enemy.
Does this mean that it's a miracle?
They just have to break in the gate and the enemy will leave?
Or does it mean that if you break in the gate, the enemy will immediately lose, Allah-u-Aalam(اللَّهُ أَعْلمَ).
But these two men told them; enter the gate and if you enter the gate, you will win.
That's all what you need to do.
Just open up that gate and walk in.
So these two men are willing to fight.
They're willing to go in and fight.
And they're encouraging their people to fight.
What quality did Allahسُبحانه وتعالى describe these two men with?
What quality do these two men have?
Fear.
يَخَافُونَ
قَالَ رَجُلَانِ يَخَافُونَ
They fear.
This is very important thing to notice that you cannot fight the enemy unless, you fear Allahسُبحانه وتعالى more than you feel the enemy.
You have to have Khash'ya(خَشْية) of Allah.
You cannot face the enemy because as a human being; you have natural fear.
You have natural fear from death.
But if you have the fear of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, and you are afraid of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى more than you are afraid of the creation,
then nothing can stand in front of you.
And that's why the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) in the sake of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; nothing can stand in front of them; nothing.
Because nothing can put fear in their hearts.
They have no fear of the creation.
The creation can present a bigger army; they can present stronger weapons
but they can never put in their hearts fear more than the fear of Allah.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
أَتَخْشَوْنَهُمْ ۚ فَٱللَّهُ أَحَقُّ أَن تَخْشَوْهُ
Do you fear them?
You need to fear Allah.
Allah is the one whom should be feared.
We should not fear the creation
and that's why the men of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى who have the Khashyah(خَشْيَه); nothing can shake their hearts.
Al-Izza-Ibn-e-Abdul-Salam(العزہ ابن عبدالسلام) when he walked and met with the leader of that At-Tatar(التتار);
an emperor who was powerful mighty leader.
Al-Izza-Ibn-e-Abdul-Salam(العزہ ابن عبدالسلام) walked in to meet with him and this man was famous with power.
He was a blood thirsty leader from, Al-Maghul(اَلْمَغُوْل) who attacked the Muslim world and was destroying everything that he would see.
In Baghdad(بغداد), they sacked it and they killed Two million.
Al-Izza-Ibn-e-Abdul-Salam(العزہ ابن عبدالسلام) went with his students to meet with this leader of At-Tatar(التتار).
So, he started speaking to him.
And then, he started raising his voice and pointing his finger in his face
and threatening him with Hellfire and threatening him with the punishment of Allah and making Dua(دُعَا) against him.
The students who came with Al-Izza-Ibn-e-Abdul-Salam(العزہ ابن عبدالسلام) started wrapping up their clothes.
Why?
They're waiting for the sword to cut his head and blood to splash all over the place.
So they were wrapping up their clothes.
So that, the blood will not splash on them.
When they walked out; they went to Al-Izza-Ibn-e-Abdul-Salam(العزہ ابن عبدالسلام) and said;
What were you doing?
How were you able to do that?
He said; When I imagined the greatness of Allah in front of my eyes, then this man became smaller than a cat.
When I imagined the greatness of Allah, this man; this mighty powerful military general became smaller than a cat.
That is the Khashyah(خَشْيَه) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So these two men said; Just break the door open, and they're gonna lose.
And they said; And put your trust in Allah if you are believers, indeed.
What was the responsibility of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) after they heard the order from Musa(موسى) and they heard the advice from these two men?
They said;
قَالُواْ يَٰمُوسَىٰٓ إِنَّا لَن نَّدْخُلَهَآ أَبَدًا مَّا دَامُواْ فِيهَا ۖ
Oh Musa(موسى)! We shall never enter it as long as they are there.
We're not going to go in; period.
Don't try.
Neither will your order work; nor will their advice do any good.
We're not gonna go in and then, look at what they said;
فَٱذْهَبْ أَنتَ وَرَبُّكَ فَقَٰتِلَآ إِنَّا هَٰهُنَا قَٰعِدُونَ۝
Go and fight with your Lord, we are sitting right here.
Qa'idoon(قَٰعِدُونَ) means; sitting down.
Look at the passiveness; sitting down, that is the state of many of us.
I want you throughout the period of the story of Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)
now we're finished with Musa(موسى) and Firaun(فرعون),
we're done with Musa(موسى) and Firaun(فرعون), you're not gonna hear about Firaun(فرعون) anymore.
Now, we're talking about Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
From now on, I want you to always think about our situation compared it, with the story of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى did not mention upto us those stories in Qur'an for historical purposes.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is mentioning for us those stories
because we are gonna fall in the same traps, but we have the guidance that will save us out of it.
That is why, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى  told us these stories.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they fell in those traps and they couldn't get out.
And they became;
اَلْمَغْضُوبِ عَلَيْهِمْ
But this Ummah(امة) will commit the same mistakes.
But because of the blessing of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; a group of them will always be on the right path.
So we want to learn about this for our own benefit.
They said; We're gonna sit down; we're not gonna do anything.
We're gonna sit down here and Falastine(فلسطين) is gonna be free.
The problems of Muslims around the world are gonna be taking care of.
As if we are saying; that the problems we are living through now, are caused by our fathers, and our children are gonna solve them.
We don't want to do anything or waiting for the Mehdi(مهدى) to come.
This is a state of passiveness.
Qa'idoon(قَٰعِدُونَ); mean sitting down.
They're not doing anything.
But they want Musa(موسى) to go and fight with his Lord.
He is your Lord, He has promised you, He's going to do you good, go with Him and fight.
Compare this with the Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
أشِيرُواعَلَيَّ أيُّها النَّاسُ
Give me your opinion; shall we fight the enemy or not?
Al-Maqdad-Ibn-Aswad(المقداد ابن اسود) stood up and said;
We are not gonna say, like what the children of Israel(اسرائيل) have said;
Go and fight with your Lord.
But we are going to say; Go and fight with your Lord; we are going to fight with you.
Musa(موسى) is one step away from Jerusalem; the promise of Allah, which he has been waiting for four years.
Musa(موسى) is almost there; he got it.
He was freed from Egypt.
Firaun(فرعون) was destroyed.
And now, they are on the Gates of Jerusalem, he can see it with his own eyes.
He can see the promise of Allah right in front of him.
And in that particular moment, Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) betrayed him.
It was a grim moment for Syedina Musaعليه السلام .
Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) after that; he raised his hand, so Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
قَالَ رَبِّ إِنِّى لَآ أَمْلِكُ إِلَّا نَفْسِى وَأَخِى ۖ فَٱفْرُقْ بَيْنَنَا وَبَيْنَ ٱلْقَوْمِ ٱلْفَٰسِقِينَ۝
He; Moses said;
Oh my Lord! I have power only over myself and my brother, so separate us from the people who are rebellious.
I have no control over these people.
I have control only on myself and my brother.
All of these are not doing me anything.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; Please separate me from the people who are rebellious.
Because he saw that this nation who he served, and he brought them and delivered them to safety,
now and when they're one step away from Jerusalem; they betrayed him and they refuse to enter.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has punish Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) because of that, and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قَالَ فَإِنَّهَا مُحَرَّمَةٌ عَلَيْهِمْ ۛ أَرْبَعِينَ سَنَةً ۛ
يَتِيهُونَ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ ۚ
Allah said; Therefore, the Holy Land is forbidden to them for 40 years.
In distraction; they will wander through the land.
فَلَا تَأْسَ عَلَى ٱلْقَوْمِ ٱلْفَٰسِقِينَ۝
So be not sorrowful over the people who are disobedient.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made them wander in the desert for 40 years
because of this sin, of refusing to fight in the sake of Allah.
So they were in a small area; Sinaa(سِيْنَا).
And they're going around in circles trying to find the way out; in a very small area, Sinaa(سِيْنَا) not very big.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made them lose directions.
So they're going in circles traveling in Sinaa(سِيْنَا) for 40 years.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wanted to meet Musa(موسى).
And He gave an appointment with Musa(موسى) to meet him after 30 days.
He said; After 30 days; we meet in the holy place next to At-Toor(الطور); next to the mountain.
وَوَاعَدْنَا مُوسَىٰ ثَلَاثِينَ لَيْلَةً
And we appointed for Musa(موسى) Thirty(30) nights.
Musa(موسى) was in a hurry to meet with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; so he went early.
The Mufassireen(مفسرين) say that, what happened was that,
Musa(موسى) was commanded to fast for 30 days because fasting is purification.
So Musa(موسى) will go through a period of purification for 30 days, before he meets with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله); fasting is a purification, Tazkiya(تَزْكِيَهْ); it is a purification for us.
So, Musa(موسى) went through that period of purification for 30 days.
Because of the smell and this is something that, some of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) say;
because of the smell of his mouth, which is natural due to the hunger;
Musa(موسى) used Miswaak(مسواك) to change that smell, and he went to meet with the Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Allah told him; Oh Musa(موسى)!
Don't you know that, I love the smell of the mouth of the person who's fasting more than I love the smell of Musk.
Go and fast another 10 days.
He said; That's the reason, why?
أَتْمَمْنَاهَا بِعَشْرٍ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; And we added 10 days to it.
So the total was 40 days.
During that period; during those 40 days; Musa(موسى) was fasting.
وَأَتْمَمْنَاهَا بِعَشْرٍ فَتَمَّ مِيقَاتُ رَبِّهِ أَرْبَعِينَ لَيْلَةً ۚ
And we appointed for Musa(موسى) 30 nights and add it to the period 10 more,
and he completed the term appointed by his Lord of 40 nights.
Musa(موسى) told his brother;
وَقَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِأَخِيهِ هَارُونَ اخْلُفْنِي فِي قَوْمِي وَأَصْلِحْ وَلَا تَتَّبِعْ سَبِيلَ الْمُفْسِدِينَ۝
Replace me among my people act in the right way, and follow not the way of the mischief makers.
So the leader of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) left;
he has to appoint somebody else to lead them and the best was the Nabi(نَبِي); Haroon(هارون).
Then Musa(موسى) went to meet Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
Allah says;
وَلَمَّا جَآءَ مُوسَىٰ لِمِيقَٰتِنَا
And when Musa(موسى) came at the time and place, appointed by us.
وَكَلَّمَهُۥ رَبُّهُۥ
And his Lord spoke to him.
Musa(موسى) went to speak with Allah.
So Musa(موسى) is Kaleem-Ullah(كَلِيْمُ الله); the one whom Allah spoke with.
And Kaleem(كَلِيْم) means; Allah spoke with him many times; not once or twice; many times.
Musa(موسى) now, reached to the level where, Allah is speaking with him.
Musa(موسى) wanted to get one step higher.
He wanted to see Allah. So he said;
رَبِّ أَرِنِىٓ أَنظُرْ إِلَيْكَ ۚ
Oh my Lord! Show me yourself; that I may look upon you.
Did Musa(موسى) say this because, he is in doubt?
No,
He said it because, he wants to achieve that high status and to enjoy the pleasure of seeing Allahسُبحانه وتعالى which is the greatest pleasure.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى);
لَن تَرَىٰ نِى
You cannot see me; you cannot see me.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى); Look at the mountain, and I'm gonna reveal myself to the mountain.
Allah was to show him; a proof that, he cannot see Allah.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is gonna show himself to the mountain and Musa(موسى) is staring at the mountain.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى revealed himself to the mountain.
And Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) says; Allah only revealed part of himself.
The mountain was destroyed and crushed down and turned into dust.
The mountain could not stand the power of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So, the mountain was crushed and destroyed and vanished, completely.
فَسَاخل جَبَل
It just went down in the earth because of humbleness to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and broke into pieces of dirt, sand.
Musa(موسى); when he saw the mountain, what happened to him?
فَخَرَّصَعِقًا
Musa(موسى) fell down in the state of shock, unconscious.
Musa(موسى) fell unconscious because of the shock by just Staring at the mountain,
what would happen to him if he was staring at the Allah?
This was the reaction of Musa(موسى) when he saw the mountain.
What would have happened to him, if he had seen Allahسُبحانه وتعالى?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمَّا تَجَلَّىٰ رَبُّهُۥ لِلْجَبَلِ جَعَلَهُۥ دَكًّا وَخَرَّ مُوسَىٰ صَعِقًا ۚ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; You cannot see me but look upon the mountain; if it stands still in its place, then you shall see me.
So when his Lord appeared to the mountain.
He said; he made it collapse to dust and Musa(موسى) fell down; unconscious.
Then Musa(موسى) said;
فَلَمَّآ أَفَاقَ قَالَ سُبْحَٰنَكَ تُبْتُ إِلَيْكَ وَأَنَا۠ أَوَّلُ ٱلْمُؤْمِنِينَ۝
Musa(موسى) said;
Glory be to You, I turn to you in repentance and I am the first of the believers.
Did anybody see Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)?
No one;
No one has seen Allahسُبحانه وتعالى with his eyes.
But Muhammadﷺ has seen Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) but not with his eyes.
He saw Him with his heart.
What does it mean that, you see Allah with your heart?
When you're dreaming, your eyes are closed but you can still see and hear.
When you dream about things; you see things; you hear things.
So some of the scholar say that, Rasool Allah ﷺ has been able to see Allah in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), with his heart but not with his eyes.
In Akhirah(آخرة); can anybody see Allah?
Who are the ones who will see Allahسُبحانه وتعالى?
Al-Mominun(اَلْمومِنُون); the believers in Jannah(جنة).
The ones who are in the lower levels of Jannah(جنة); they would see Allahسُبحانه وتعالى every Jummah(جُمعَه).
In the time of Salat-ul-Jummah(صَلوةُ الْجُمعَه); the people of Jannah(جنة) will go to a certain meeting place;
and their seats will be reserved ahead of time.
That's in the Hadith(حديث), You can just go and pick a spot and sit.
You have the leisure to do that in the Masjid(مسجد), you can come and pick a spot.
But there in Jannah(جنة) you cannot, the seats are already reserved; and on what basis are they reserved?
How close you are to the Khateeb(خطيب) on Jummah(جُمعَه); that's in the Hadith(حديث).
The seats; the closer you were to the Imam(اِمَام) in Salat-ul-Jummah(صَلوةُ الْجُمعَه);
the closer you are going to be to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى on those meetings on Jummah(جُمعَه).
So here in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), you can come and pick that spot; the earlier you come; the better spot and the closest spot you'll get.
So you have the freedom of choosing this place; when you are in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
but in Akhirah(آخرة); that's it, it's reserved.
And the ones who used to sit in the first Saff(صَف); they are the ones who will receive the first Saff(صَف); the first line in Jannah(جنة).
That is for the lower ranks of Jannah(جنة).
And then the people of Firdaus(فِردَوس); the higher levels; they would see Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, twice a day.
That is for the people of the higher levels of Jannah(جنة).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; as we have mentioned earlier; has punished Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)
because of their refusal to enter into the Holy Land with wandering in the wilderness for 40 years; Ateh(اطیع).
It was a punishment from Allah.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is very merciful and forgiving.
So even though, it was a punishment for them;
they were asking Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and Allah was accepting their Dua(دُعَا).
They wanted food; they wanted water; they wanted shade; and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was providing for them.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَظَلَّلْنَا عَلَيْكُمُ الْغَمَامَ وَأَنزَلْنَا عَلَيْكُمُ الْمَنَّ وَالسَّلْوَىىٰ ۖ كُلُوا مِن طَيِّبَاتِ مَا رَزَقْنَاكُمْ ۖ
And we shaded you with clouds and send down on you; Al-Mann(اَلْمَن) and As-Salwa(اَلسَّلوى).
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided them with clouds that is the shade to protect them from the sun.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided them with food and drink.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided for them shade and provided for them; Al-Mann-Wa-Salwa(اَلمَن وَالسَّلوى).
Al-Mann-Wa-Salwa(اَلمَن وَالسَّلوى); The Mufassireen(مفسرين) have tried to explain, what it is exactly but;
it is a blessing from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to something special; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent for them.
Some of them said that, Al-Mann(اَلْمَن) and As-Salwa(اَلسَّلوى);
Al-Mann(اَلْمَن) is some kind of extracts that come out from trees and it tastes like; honey.
And some of them have mentioned that, it is honey.
As-Salwa(اَلسَّلوى); most of Mufassireen(مفسرين) say; it's a bird.
Even though, Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) were going through a stage of punishment.
Because, this was supposed to be a punishment for them; why?
Because they refuse to enter into; Al-Ardul Muqaddasa(اَلاَرْض المُقدَّسَ).
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
يَتُوبُ عَلَى التَّائِبِين
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى accept the repentance of the ones who repent.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gives the human beings many chances.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has sent to Firaun(فرعون); nine Ayaat(آيات); Tis'ie Ayaat(تِسْعِى آيات ); one Ayah(آية) after another; giving Firaun(فرعون) a chance
but in the end; when Firaun(فرعون) refuse to accept any of them, then the punishment of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى came.
And when the punishment of Allah comes down; nothing can release it.
So, with Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided them with this food, Al-Mannu-Wa-Salwa(اَلمَن وَالسَّلوى) is the food.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided them with the shade.
What else do they need?
They need water.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; And remember when Musa(موسى) asked for water for his people,
the people came and asked Musa(موسى); we want water.
So Musa(موسى) made Istisqa(اِسْتَسْقَىٰ); he asked Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to give them water.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
إِذِ ٱسْتَسْقَىٰ مُوسَىٰ لِقَوْمِهِۦ فَقُلْنَا ٱضْرِب بِّعَصَاكَ ٱلْحَجَرَ ۖ فَٱنفَجَرَتْ مِنْهُ ٱثْنَتَا عَشْرَةَ عَيْنًا ۖ
قَدْ عَلِمَ كُلُّ أُنَاسٍۢ مَّشْرَبَهُمْ ۖ
كُلُواْ وَٱشْرَبُواْ مِن رِّزْقِ ٱللَّهِ وَلَا تَعْثَوْاْ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ مُفْسِدِينَ۝
And Musa(موسى) asked Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, to provide the Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) with water.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى); Hit the stone with your stick; 12 springs of water are gonna gush forth.
For every tribe of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they have their own spring.
So the stick that Musa(موسى) had remember a long time ago, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى);
وَمَا تِلْكَ بِيَمِينِكَ يَا مُوسَى۝
What's in your hand, Musa(موسى)?
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى knows the stick more than Musa(موسى).
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has provided for Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); the food; Al-Mannu-Wa-Salwa(اَلمَن وَالسَّلوى) and the shade.
وَظَلَّلْنَا عَلَيْكُمُ الْغَمَامَ
and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى also provided for them; the water.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they went to Musa(موسى), they asked Musa(موسى) to make Dua(دُعَا) for them.
What did they want?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِذْ قُلْتُمْ يَا مُوسَىٰ لَن نَّصْبِرَ عَلَىٰ طَعَامٍ وَاحِدٍ فَادْعُ لَنَا رَبَّكَ يُخْرِجْ لَنَا مِمَّا تُنبِتُ الْأَرْضُ مِن بَقْلِهَا
فَادْعُ لَنَا رَبَّكَ يُخْرِجْ لَنَا مِمَّا تُنبِتُ الْأَرْضُ مِن بَقْلِهَا وَقِثَّائِهَا وَفُومِهَا وَعَدَسِهَا وَبَصَلِهَا ۖ
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they went to Musa(موسى)
and remember, when you said; Oh Musa(موسى)! We cannot endure one kind of food.
So invoke your Lord for us to bring forth for us of what the earth grows;
it's herbs; it's cucumbers; it's Foom(فُوم), which is either wheat or garlic; it's lentils and it's onions.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided them with, Al-Mann-Wa-Salwa(اَلمَن وَالسَّلوى); special food from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى for Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
They went to Musa(موسى) and they said; Oh Musa(موسى)! tell Allahسُبحانه وتعالى that, we cannot endure having one type of food.
We want to have more variety in the menu.
And they asked for; lentils, onions, garlic, and herbs.
And other stuff that grows from the earth; vegetarians.
All the stuff they want are some kinds of plants that come out from the earth.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is providing them with the best meat; special meat.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is providing them with this special food which is Al-Mann(اَلْمَن); we don't even know what it is.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is giving them this as a blessing and as a miracle.
It's a miracle and the same time, it's a blessing for them.
They went to Musa(موسى) and they said; we got tired of eating the same type of food; we want to have more variety.
So ask Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to provide us with other stuff; other kinds of food.
Keep in mind that the issue here is not the particular types of food.
The issue here is not garlic and onion, and cucumbers and herbs.
Even though, their particular choice of these foods is amazing,
because how could you replace the meat, and the Manna(مَنَّ) and Salwa(سَلْوى) with garlic and onion.
I mean, this shows you their tastes, but the issue is not in the particular types of food; they're requesting.
The issue here we need to keep in mind is that, Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are refusing to sacrifice.
They're not even willing to give up the type of foods that they grew up with.
They grew up in Egypt; eating onion and garlic and cucumbers and these herbs.
If they grew up in Egypt; eating big Macro-Whopper, they're gonna ask for the same thing.
So the issue here is not particularly the garlic and the onion, the lentils;
the issue here is that they're not willing to give up; even, their daily habits, for the sake of Allah.
Why did they leave from Egypt?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى brought them out of Egypt, to free them; and to honour them,
and to give them the Holy Land which they have been promised.
But freedom has a price, and entering into the Holy Land needs some work.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they are not willing to even give up, the particular types of food they were eating;
let alone work, and sacrifice, and pay for their freedom.
So, Musa(موسى) told them;
اهْبِطُوا مِصْرًا فَإِنَّ لَكُمْ مَا سَأَلْتُمْ
Go back to Egypt! You will find what you want.
If you don't want the freedom, if you don't want the honor, if you don't want the Holy Land; go back to Egypt!
Go back to the life of slavery; to the life of servitude; to the life of humility; to the life of oppression.
And you will find all the lentils, garlic, onion that you want.
If you're not even willing to give up a small portion of your lifestyle,
if you're not willing to give up a habit that you grew up with;
how can you pay the price for freedom?
You don't deserve freedom.
If you're not even willing to change the menu, if you're not willing to change the types of food that you eat,
then you don't deserve the freedom and the honour.
They want the Holy Land; they want freedom; they want Firaun(فرعون) to be destroyed.
They want to have the establishment; the Tamkeen(تمکین) on the earth,
but they don't want to do anything; they don't want to sacrifice anything; they don't even want to give up their daily habits.
It may sound very strange, how could such a people do this?
How could they go and ask Musa(موسى), we want lentils and onion and garlic;
when Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is providing them with Mann(مَن) and Salwa(سَلْوى); sounds very strange.
But remember, always when we're talking about these stories of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) and Musa(موسى); relate them to our situation.
You gonna find that it's not very different.
If you look at our situation, and remember, what we said earlier that,
everything that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has mentioned about Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)
there are gonna be some people from this ummah(امة) who are gonna fall into the same mistake.
The difference between our ummah(امة); the ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) is that,
with Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); it was a general problem, and it ended up causing the wrath of Allah to be on them.
But with the ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ the problem will be with some,
but there are going to be some who are continuously on the straight path.
That is the difference.
لا تزال طائفة من أمتي ظاهرين على الحق،لا يضرهم من خالفهم حتى تقوم الساعة
There will be a group of my ummah(امة) on the straight path.
Any disagreement with them will not harm them until, the day of judgment.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ also says;
لتتبعن سنن من كان قبلكم، حذو القُذَّةِ بالقُذَّة، حتى لو دخلوا جُحْرَ ضَبٍّ لدخلتموه
You will follow the footsteps of the nations before you, step by step, inch by inch,
even if, they enter into a hole of a lizard; you're gonna follow them there.
The Sahabah(صحابه) said; Al-Yahoodu-wan-Nasara(اليهود والنّصارى); the Christians and the Jews, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
فمن أيضا
Who else!
So, there's gonna be some of the ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ; who are going to follow the footsteps of the Jews and the Christians
and they are going to be some of the Muslims, who are going to learn the lesson and not commit the same mistake.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) refused to pay the price.
They didn't want to give up anything for the sake of freedom, and for the sake of Allah, and for the sake of establishment.
And we find that, our situation is not very different.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) refuse to give up the habit of eating garlic and onions and lentils;
while, we have some who are not willing to give up a football game, or a basketball game and come to Salah(صلوة).
If the game is in the time of salat-ul-Isha(صلوةالعشاء) or Salat-ul-Asr(صلوةالعصر) or Salat-ul-Maghrib(صلوةالمغرب);
I'm not gonna leave the TV set and go to the Masjid(مسجد); I'm not gonna leave.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); at least, this was an issue of food.
Here, we're talking about something that doesn't benefit but it harm;
sitting in front of the tube box, watching a basketball game or watching a soccer game or a football game and leaving the Salah(صلوة).
Or another habit to see, because we're talking about here; breaking a habit.
We're not even willing to break a habit for the sake of Allah.
You could have someone who wakes up 7: 30 in the morning, every day.
Salat-ul-Fajr(صلوةالفجر); the time ends by Shuruk-As-Shams(شُرُك الشَّمس), so it's too late to pray Fajr(فجر) now.
While, you know I can't sacrifice my sleep; I'm not gonna wake up early.
But you are willing, why are you waking up 7:30?
Because of work.
I'm willing to wake up 7:30, and sacrifice for work;
but I'm not; not willing to wake up for Salat-ul-Fajr(صلوةالفجر).
إِنَّ الصَّلَاةَ كَانَتْ عَلَى الْمُؤْمِنِينَ كِتَابًا مَّوْقُوتًا۝
The Salah(صلوة) has to be done in the specific time.
If you intentionally plan to pray Salah(صلوة) after it's time; it's unaccepted.
If you intentionally plan to pray Fajr(فجر), after the time of Fajr(فجر) is over; it is unacceptable Salah(صلوة),
because you're doing it intentionally.
It is forgiven when you're doing it with an excuse;
like you slept unintentionally, or you forgot, or you were in very extreme situation; you couldn't pray,
then you can make Qadaa(قضا) and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will forgive it.
But if you intentionally plan on a daily basis to delay the Salah(صلوة) until, the time is over; that Salah(صلوة) was unaccepted,
because it past the time.
We looked at our situation, we find that there's a lot to learn from this story.
We're not willing to give up our habits.
We're talking about giving time or giving effort or giving money, we hold back.
The religion of Allah is not something that, we can take lightly.
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
يَٰيَحْيَىٰ خُذِ ٱلْكِتَٰبَ بِقُوَّةٍۢ ۖ
Oh Yahya(يحيى)! take the book with strength.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); Take this religion with strength.
You have to take it with seriousness.
Musa(موسى) told his people;
قَالَ أَتَسْتَبْدِلُونَ الَّذِي هُوَ أَدْنَىٰ بِالَّذِي هُوَ خَيْرٌ ۚ
Do you exchange; that which is better for that, which is lower?
How can you replace; Manna(مَنَّ) and Salwa(سَلْوى) with garlic, onion and lentils.
Allah is providing you with the best, and you're asking for lowest.
اهْبِطُوا مِصْرًا فَإِنَّ لَكُم مَّا سَأَلْتُمْ ۗ
The Mufassireen(مفسرين) say; this could mean either one of two things.
اهْبِطُوا مِصْرًا
Misr(مصر) means; Egypt, but it can also mean; land.
So it would mean; go to Egypt, you will find what you want.
Go back to Egypt, you will find the garlic, lentils, onions and herbs; you are looking for.
And you will also find the oppression and the servitude and the slavery that you deserve to live under.
Or the other meaning would be;
اهْبِطُوا مِصْرًا فَإِنَّ لَكُم مَّا سَأَلْتُمْ ۗ
Go to any country or land; you're going to find this.
Manna(مَنَّ) and Salwa(سَلْوى) is the special thing; but this garlic and onion and lentil, you'll find that anywhere.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَضُرِبَتْ عَلَيْهِمُ الذِّلَّةُ وَالْمَسْكَنَةُ
And they were covered with humiliation and misery.
Because of this, they refused;
they refuse to sacrifice for Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has made on them humility and misery.
When Musa(موسى) went to meet with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in At-Toor(الطور),
and we talked about Musa(موسى) asking to see Allahسُبحانه وتعالى,
and we talked about the conversation between Allah and Musa(موسى);
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى);
وَمَآ أَعْجَلَكَ عَن قَوْمِكَ يَٰمُوسَىٰ۝
Why were you in a hurry to meet me and leave your people?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has made an appointment with Musa(موسى).
So Musa(موسى) is very urgent to go and meet with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So, he's going in a hurry.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى ask Musa(موسى);
وَمَآ أَعْجَلَكَ عَن قَوْمِكَ يَٰمُوسَىٰ۝
And what made you hasten from your people, Oh Musa(موسى)!
Musa(موسى) said;
قَالَ هُمْ أُوْلَآءِ عَلَىٰٓ أَثَرِى وَعَجِلْتُ إِلَيْكَ رَبِّ لِتَرْضَىٰ۝
He said; They are close on my footsteps.
And I hasten to you, Oh my Lord! That you might be pleased.
So Musa(موسى) left his people close by, and he went to meet with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Musa(موسى) did not leave his people alone, but he appointed his brother to be the leader in his absence.
He appointed Haroon(هارون);
وَخْلُفْنِى فِى قَوْمِى
Be my successor on my people.
And he went to meet with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى); What was going on?
Musa(موسى) did not know, what was happening?
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him; what was happening in that same moment.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قَالَ فَإِنَّا قَدْ فَتَنَّا قَوْمَكَ مِن بَعْدِكَ وَأَضَلَّهُمُ السَّامِرِيُّ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Verily, we have tried your people in your absence, and As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) has led them astray.
Allah said; We are putting your people through a test, and As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) is leading them astray.
This is a man who's called As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) from Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل), he has led them astray.
What did As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) do?
As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ); Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gave him the ability to see something, nobody else saw.
قَالَ بَصُرْتُ بِمَا لَمْ يَبْصُرُوا بِهِ
I have seen what they were not able to see.
What did he see?
When Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was destroying Firaun(فرعون) and his army; Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) was there.
The Mufassireen(مفسرين) say that Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل); whenever he would step or his horse would step on a piece of land,
life would immediately grow up from that place; from the footstep.
As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) saw Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) it's an unusual; supernatural ability that As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) had.
It's a Fitnah(فِتْنَه); it's a trial from Allah.
So As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) went, and he picked up some of that dirt from under the footsteps of the horse of Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل).
And he kept that dirt with him.
Then As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) told Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) to gather all of the gold that they have brought with them from Egypt.
The woman of Egypt; the Egyptian woman; they had their jewellery with the woman of the children of Israel(اسرائيل).
The woman of the children of Israel(اسرائيل) somehow, had the gold that belonged to the Egyptian woman.
They were feeling guilty because of that gold.
This gold doesn't belong to us, what shall we do with it?
They had a feeling of guilt.
As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) suggested that, they gather all of this gold together, and they burn it.
And then they made out of it a calf; Ijl(عِجل).
And what did As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) do?
He threw that dirt that he had with him in the gold.
So it was mixed with the gold, and they molded out of that gold; the shape of Ijl(عِجل); calf.
Somehow, that calf would make a sound, Khuwar(خوار); which is the sound of a cow, as if it was alive.
Some of the commentators of Qur'an says that; what As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) did?
He made a hole throughout the inside of the animal.
So wind would go in it with make a breezing or whistling sound, so that people would think, it's alive.
Some of them would say; somehow, it was a miracle and because of that dirt in it; it had some sort of life in it.
It wasn't alive, but it was making some sounds.
It was making a sound.
And this was a Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); when they saw this calf, made out of Gold, making this sound.
As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) told them; This is your God, so they started worshiping it.
And they were making Sujood(سجود) and Ibadah(عبادة) to the calf.
They were worshiping it.
Musa(موسى) told his people that, I'm gonna be absent for how long?
30 days.
Because the appointments in the beginning was 30.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى); add another 10 days.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) did not know that the appointment was changed;
Musa(موسى) did not tell them about the change in time.
So they thought, it was 30 days.
30 days past; 31 days past; 32 days past; where is Musa(موسى)?
They said; Musa(موسى) forgot, where his God is.
He got lost; he did not know that his God is right here.
فَنَسِيَ
He forgot.
They added another evidence.
Number one is that, this calf is making this special sound.
Number Two; Musa(موسى) was said, he's gonna be absent for 30 days and now, he's absent for more than 30 days.
They said;
هَٰذَا إِلَٰهُكُمْ وَإِلَٰهُ مُوسَىٰ فَنَسِيَ۝
This is your god and the god of Musa(موسى); but he forgot.
So this is the story behind the calf.
And we'll get back to that in the end of the story.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ